Guide to the Stanford Teacher Education Program Audio-Visual Materials
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford Teacher Education Program audio-visual materials
1952-1982
SC0522
Stanford Teacher Education Program
14.25 Linear feet
Collection consists largely of 16mm films, magnetic sound tracks, and one filmstrip from a film series for elementary school math teachers produced by the School Mathematics Study Group (SMSG), 1963; other items include filmstrips on school design, 1952-1959, and several video tapes of math and science lectures by Stanford professors, 1981-82.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer, 1995.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Description of the Collection
Collection consists largely of 16mm films, magnetic sound tracks, and one filmstrip from a film series for elementary school math teachers produced by the School Mathematics Study Group (SMSG), 1963; other items include filmstrips on school design, 1952-1959, and several video tapes of math and science lectures by Stanford professors, 1981-82.
Access Terms
School Mathematics Study Group.; Stanford Teacher Education Program; Stanford University. Graduate School of Education.; Mathematics --Study and teaching (Elementary).; Motion pictures; School buildings.; Science--Study and teaching.; Videorecordings.
Collection Contents
- Audiovisual material
  - 16MM FILMS
    - Solid Figures, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 1)
    - Ratio, rate, percent, lecture XXIV, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 1)
    - Division techniques, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 1)
    - Linear and angular measure, lecture XVI, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 1)
    - Metric properties of figures, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 1)
    - Introducing rational numbers, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 1)
    - Multiplication techniques, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 2)
    - Factors and primes, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 2)
    - Addition and subtraction of rational numbers, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 2)
    - Equivalent fractions, lecture XIX, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 2)
    - Addition and subtraction techniques, lecture VII, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 2)
    - Division, lecture IX, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 2)
    - Decimals, lecture XXIII, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 3)
    - Division of rational numbers, lecture XXII, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 3)
    - Multiplication of rational numbers, lecture XXI, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 3)
    - Congruence and similarity, lecture XXV, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 3)
    - Points, lines, planes, lecture XIII, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 3)
    - Measurement of solids, lecture XXVIII, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 3)
    - Place value and addition, lecture V, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 4)
    - Sentences, number line, lecture XII, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 4)
    - Area, lecture XXVII, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 4)
    - Names of numbers, lecture III, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 4)
    - Non-decimal positional systems, lecture IV, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 4)
    - Multiplication, lecture VIII, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 4)
    - Addition and subtraction, lecture VI, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 4)
    - Polygons and angles, lecture XIV, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 5)
    - Real numbers, lecture XXX, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 5)
    - Negative rational numbers, lecture XXIX, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 5)
    - Pre-number ideas, lecture 1, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 5)
    - Whole numbers, lecture 2, 1963; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 5)
  - VIDEOS, FILMSTRIPS, AND AUDIO TAPES
    - Dr. Nel Noddings, 7/27/81, problem solving in algebra, tape 1 and 2, 1981; 2 videotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 6)
    - Microteaching, science, 1982 Aug 2; 1 Video tape (reel to reel) (Box 6)
    - Ann Schwarberg, Celia Henderson, Laura Tucker, 8/4/82, 1982; 1 Video tape (reel to reel) (Box 6)
    - Vicky Noddings, Gerry Moninger (?), John Kerwin, 8/5/82, 1982; 1 Video tape (reel to reel) (Box 6)
    - S-J. Brodkey, Brandon lee, Cheryl Lewis, 8/5/82, 1982; 1 Video tape (reel to reel) (Box 6)
    - Rubin, Ed. 240, July 11, 1975 and August 8, 1975 (2 cassettes), 2 audiocassette(s) (Box 6)
    - Nathaniel Gage's guide to the Teacher Training Automat (audio-visual materials), 1 Notebook (Box 6)
    - SMSG (School Mathematics Study Group) visuals I, II, III, IV (5 copies each), 20 Filmstrip(s) (Box 7)
    - NEA, Breakthrough to Better Schools, 1 Filmstrip(s) (Box 7)
    - AASA, School Buildings, 1957 and 1959, 1957, 1959; 2 Filmstrip(s) (Box 7)
    - 1952 Contemporary School Design: sites and building exteriors, 1 Filmstrip(s) (Box 7)
    - 1952 Contemporary School Design: interiors of large group spaces, 1 Filmstrip(s) (Box 7)
  - MAGNETIC SOUND TRACKS
    - Multiplication, lecture 8, 1963; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 8)
    - Addition and subtraction techniques, lecture VII, 1963; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 8)
    - Addition and subtraction, lecture VI, 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 8)
    - Polygons and angles, lecture XIV, m.s.t, 1963; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 8)
    - Sentences, number line, lecture XII, 1963; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 8)
    - Solid figures, lecture XXVI, 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 8)
    - Names for numbers, lecture III, 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Whole numbers, lecture II, 1963; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Pre-number ideas, lecture I, 1963; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Numeration systems, 1963; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Place value and addition, lecture V, 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Division techniques, lecture XI, 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Multiplication techniques, 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Decimals, 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Ratio, rate, percent, lecture XXIV, 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Congruence and similarity, lecture XXV, 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Area, lecture XXVII, 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Division of rational numbers, lecture XXII, 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Multiplication of rational numbers, lecture XXI, 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Addition and substraction of rational numbers, 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Factors and primes, lecture XVII, 1963; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Equivalent fractions, lecture XIX, 1963; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Introducing rational numbers, lecture XVIII, 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Linear and angular measure, lecture XV, 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Metric properties of figures, lecture XV, 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Negative rational numbers, lecture XXIX, 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Real numbers, lecture XXX, 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Measurement of solids, lecture XXVIII, 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Division, lecture IX, 1963; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Points, lines and planes, lecture XIII, 1963; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)